this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software for software engineering radio
this is Nana Salinas today I have with
me Charlie burger Charlie burger is the
senior director of product management
for Oracle's machine learning and
advanced analytics Charlie has over 30
years of experience in data analysis and
has worked at Oracle Thinking Machines
Corporation Honeywell among many others
he's responsible for the product
management of Oracle's machine learning
data mining predictive analytics text
mining statistical functions and works
with Oracle customers and other Oracle
applications development teams to design
and deploy predictive analytics through
the enterprise previously he was the VP
of Product Management and marketing at
Thinking Machines Corporation Charlie is
also a Technical Evangelist
he holds a Master of Science in
manufacturing engineering and a Master
of Business Administration from Boston
University he also holds a Bachelor of
Science in operations research and
industrial engineering from the
University of Massachusetts at Amherst
today we will talk about machine
learning and predictive applications
charlie welcome to software engineering
radio thank you for having me
thank you you work at Oracle in machine
learning and advanced analytics and
predictive applications what is a
predictive application well a predictive
application is simply taking a
predictive model that you've built that
may have in the past been left on a you
know on a laptop or a single server or
an open-source package and it's putting
that into the enterprise putting that
into some sort of production or
operationalizing that that predictive
model that's where it's all yeah that's
what it's all about is putting your your
insights and your prediction
to some sort of you know real-time
operational kind of a situation I'm
always impressed that when I go to my my
bank and I go the ATM machine and I
slept like my card and stick it in the
ATM machine and the very first question
to ask is hello Charley burger you know
what language do you want to use as if
that may have changed and what I would
expect today in 2017 is for it to have
observed all my previous behaviors and
transactions and for it to come back
with a suggestion or a recommendation
that says hello Charley burger would you
like to take out an extra hundred
dollars cash like I've noticed you
usually do on Friday nights getting
ready for the weekend so that's what I
really would call operationalizing a
predictive model we do a predictive
application that's a good point learn
from the previous data and a lot of
enterprises are using predictive
applications more and more before these
existed what were companies doing was
there no predictive analysis no
predictive analysis has been around of
course for years I think it goes all the
way back of course to Bayes Way back in
the 1700s with is you know Bayes theorem
and conditional probabilities and people
have always been you know looking at
patterns and things but oftentimes in
the old days I guess it would be in
their heads later on it might be some
sort of statistical model using the data
sampling and building some sort of
regression or some sort of model based
on on that but but over the last say 20
years or so neural networks this
decision trees clustering a bunch of
different machine learning algorithms
and tools and software and open-source
have all emerged and it's really a fun
and exciting time these days there's so
much going on but many of the machine
learning news cases were something like
I took a set of data I analyzed it
I used this algorithm I got a slightly
better result and a better fit or I used
this album you got an even better fit so
there were too many I guess published
papers too many people doing sort of you
know laboratory experiments in their in
their office or on their desktop and
never actually worrying about getting
production now the database marketing
field I think was one of the earlier
fields that did this just because that
was their business they would you know
take data out of a oftentimes a
relational database move it to something
like a traditional software package or
perhaps more recently perhaps open
source but they build the models in a
separate analytical environment and then
they would somehow need to take those
predictions and take the models and
score them against the data that's uh
where's that data it's oftentimes in a
in a data repository or a database or
something and that was a very sort of
outer loop process and they do that very
mechanical very outer loop and then they
then they'd have a list of people and
then maybe they'd send you the email or
make the phone call to you or something
like that but it wasn't that much more
real-time operationalized kind of a
deployment of machinery that you would
more and more expect today mm-hmm yes
what you're talking about now is we used
we have people working in a laboratory
doing the experiments but the data is
somewhere else so they take the data and
to use it in the models and we'll
actually talk about this later on and
also about the other idea of moving the
models to where the data is but before
we talk about that I want to understand
more about predictive applications like
you said before we would have the models
but the applications were really being
built why do you think we are building
them more now well it's because it's the
art of the possible it's what people can
do these days there's so much data and
digital exhaust from from people it's
the data fication of everything in these
days so you have so much more fertile
inputs to to pretend and and do just
about anything and you see that all the
time things like I think it's called
fair cast or that will predict whether
or not when you buy an airline ticket is
it likely to know the price to go up or
down and
on your droid row he's getting
recommended stories and you're getting
things all over the place we're also an
Oracle we we have a lot of enterprise
customers and a lot of developers that
that they want to build enterprise
applications that's been sort of our our
strong strong sweeper for some time and
like we've had these Oracle code events
that that have once you developers come
in and say well I I have this whole
ecosystem of building things around the
enterprise data and the enterprise
applications oh I want to enhance them
and do more so what they were able to do
is is just leave the data right where it
is and build some sort of you know
predictive application but they're able
to do it so much more more easily well
can I tell about an example application
would that help yes you get you can
mention that example if you want well I
just it to me it's a it's a very good
example it kind of sets the stage for a
pearl for all of them you could imagine
an application we actually have
something called uh Oracle human capital
management
it's called Oracle Juden Capital
Management and there's a there's a
module in there called workforce
predictions and so what that does I mean
it's just sort of basic it says okay I
know each employee I know their salary I
know where they stand compared to their
peers I know what their dental plans are
how many children they have I know how
long they've reported into the same
manager I know maybe the managers
reviews or the employees reviews I have
I have lots and lots of variables and a
lot of derived variables that I can use
or for inputs and so what you can do and
what we've done is just say well I'll
take all that and I will build
predictive models and predict the
likelihood that any employee is likely
to voluntarily leave the corporation we
also predict their performance but we
don't do it as a separate outer loop or
you know the data science has been long
ago automated so what you do as a
manager you go into your your
application you just see your employees
and you see like like high surf warnings
almost like watch out this guy our woman
is is a is maybe more likely to
voluntarily leave us and then somebody
else and then because because it's a
real predictive application you know I
just
here right you don't want to say well
you know Joe or sue we're really likely
to leave you want to say well why so you
need to sort of interrogate the model
and find out you know in the simple
sense you'd say what the coefficients
are but it could be any variety of
models but you want to know the reasons
why and it may say bonus
well maybe the bonus was really high or
maybe it was really low it was high
enough that they could retire or quit or
buy an island or maybe it was too low or
maybe it was good but maybe compared to
their peers you need to have this sort
of just-in-time
communication of what we mean by the
model sort of the explanation of why
that prediction was made and then and
then you really would if you take it
further it say well I'd really like to
before I give them a person on a bonus
or change their title or or have them
will forgive some sick days or whatever
I want to do I'd like to do what if
analysis so what you can do is you can
actually have a little slider bar and
you can say well what if I you know
forget I have a discussion with the
person I kind of they have a sick
grandmother and they've been taking a
lot of sick days for themselves maybe if
I take my slider bar and say what if I
were to give them 25 sick days well what
would other level for Java programmers
you know typically do and you get a
prediction of that and you can make a
decision so they're on the fly so it's
it's that type of you know interactive
predictive in application and I think is
just becoming the expectation these days
yep and in this example that you
mentioned the main consumers of it are
managers the HR department for other
types of predictive applications within
the enterprise what are other consumers
that can exist oh eight minutes a
Crockett's across the board there was a
great book I'm gonna mention probably a
couple of books along the way called Big
Data by Victor Meyer shoenberger and
kind of Cukor I'm just looking at myself
over here great book and in there they
talk about how in New York City the fire
department had way too many buildings to
try and inspect so they got a bunch of
data about each of the different
buildings and they build predictive
models and one of the factors were you
know did the person who
was me managing that ability they take
out a permit to do maybe some brick
repair on the outside or to fix the
plumbing in order to do different things
and those kind of pieces of data
predictive in nature of whether or not
that building was being maintained well
and was maybe not a crack house or a
fire hazard or something like that so if
you have limited resources and you're
driving around as a fireman and you're
an inspector and you need to do building
inspections you would put those houses
that were mounth well-maintained as you
know through this prediction lower on
the list and you'd sort of prioritize
your resources and and we see those kind
of things you know more and more these
days and they expect quite a bit more in
the in the days to come
yeah why do you think is making these
applications more common is it the
technology specs yeah I think it's I
think it's what I think of it as is the
you know what they call the data
fication of everything everything is
been digitalized you have data you have
higher performing computers you have
advances in machine learning you put all
these things together and you have a
very powerful soup that can do a lot of
very you know you know theydon't
things and you also have greater and
greater expectations I don't know about
you but when I go to when I go on
vacation and I go do you know yeah I
really paramount of sci-fi kind of books
but when I go on vacation I have no idea
what book I'm going to read but I just
got a Amazon and I look at my past books
that I've purchased I look at
recommendations and I'll review the
recommendations and I'll buy that book
it's just sort of the expectation so if
I'm a salesperson for example I would
expect that before I start dialing for
dollars calling people that I would have
a list presented to me or an interactive
application or or maybe on my mobile
droid it would say go see Charlie and
selling this product because he really
really needs that product per my
prediction I think they'll see that you
know really across the board more and
more yes exactly
one of my co-workers actually for his
son's birthday he got
whatever Amazon recommended and he said
his son really liked it so yeah it's it
it I think the future is gonna be a lot
of fun because it just keeps on getting
better better better you'll have less
and less of these uh you know what are
they call it scooping phone calls trying
to sell you something and you'll have if
the phone does ring you'll know it's a
good thing and we've been talking about
this data fication time where can the
data come from for a predictive
application what are some examples oh
geez I mean this is where you kind of
run the gamut of are we talking about
what people are doing yesterday or or
today or vary in this sort of very near
future what I mean our what are some
examples of data sources like logs or
information from IOT just in general for
predictive applications that are being
built or have been built what are the
sources of of that data well I mean I
think I think you have a you know it's
all over the place Facebook pics if I
have facial recognition and you see me
as a as a Boston person because I'm
based in the Boston area and you see me
standing next to pictures of New York
Yankees or New York Jets football teams
and you do facial recognition
you're gonna earring a suspect that you
know I've gone crazy or something right
here so that would be a source tweets of
course if I change money address any
kind of uh I mean there's there's a lot
of data that I think people talk about
and people also highlight in demos the
demo is always somebody that's stuck on
out some water of an important person
that's talking stuck on a plane and does
a tweet and had we only known that we
could have saved the stock price of this
airline so so those are all the demos in
reality and I think it's a lot more of
the kind of data you can just get from
data providers like Epsilon
as a native cloud there's a lot of
providers that will provide data to you
you know last I looked at I think
epsilon I believe had something like
eight I know I'll probably get it wrong
but I think it was eight hundred and
fifty variables on every uh you know man
woman and child if you will so they know
your age your income they know the
average income in your zip code they
know the Bluebook value of car one two
and three some of the customers I've
been dealing with know they know what my
spend is in each major hotel chain on
room on restaurant on alcohol on parking
and so on knowing all that information
you can do some pretty good predictions
you mentioned epsilon what's epsilon
epsilon is a purveyor I guess of data
they also do a lot of analytics so the
way I think of epsilon and I know I'm
probably going to sell them short a
little bit but epsilon has if you want
to let's say you and I wanted to start
up a business selling yachts to
different people one did not target
everyone who you know not everyone's
gonna be able to afford a yacht or live
near the ocean so we might go to epsilon
and say do you have any information
about customers because we want to
filter on just those people that make
maybe a more than a million dollars a
year
subscribe to yachting magazine and live
close fifty miles are closer to the oak
to a large body of water so that's the
type of data they would have there's
other different data providers these
days I won't mention them all but
epsilon is one that's very well-known
and popular Oracle has their own Oracle
data cloud where we also have that type
of data as well
it's from the only answer on beta logics
and it was their original company but
but in the case of epsilon which I know
I guess I'd say I am some yeah I have
five public reference customers that are
using that DX marketing is is a public
reference customer that uses the epsilon
data set and it's bad I think it's eight
hundred and fifty fields attributes and
is what we call them in the database but
variables about really everyone every
evening
and woman and child pretty much is the
way I think of it so they know your age
your income they know the income and
ethnicity of your zip code they know
your what magazines if you subscribe to
they knew the blue book about they know
how many cars you have it they know the
blue book value of those cars and if you
think of all the myriad of variables you
might never possible possibly assemble
on an individual and try and take that
all the way out to eight hundred and
fifty fields of information you know
they have a lot of data I was I was I
was thinking also of if you ever want to
see a really good use case of just
having a lot of data and analyzing it
well look at some of the YouTube videos
and what Cambridge analytic I did during
the United States presidential election
there's some famous videos they are
about just you know the level of detail
they had and how they use it machine
learning you know to target people who
were more likely to vote one way or the
other now that is a little bit more of
what I'd call a one-off right it's a
every four years you may put that much
effort into something you may have a
list you might send your your people out
to knock on doors or make phone calls it
still would need to be made much more
into a sort of an application a
real-time application you know if you
think of maybe putting that inside of a
phone booth or in a voting booth or
something I think that's probably
illegal but but that's the type of idea
of just deploying real-time predictions
and insights where whenever and wherever
it's most appropriate and earlier in the
show we talked about the people that
work in the labs and how they're
disconnected from the data and a lot of
people build applications this way it's
a common way to architect it can you
explain in a little more detail what
this architecture looks like Oh what
most people do when they when they build
a predictive model and you know we've
all done it you know the first thing you
do is you go down to your your I don't
know your DBA and whatever you know
wherever they're storing their corporate
data and you say can I have an extract
of that data and I need the following
attributes on these
records and and you in the DBA probably
is busy and maybe they get around to it
they finally give you an extract and the
first thing you do is you don't want to
say sneakernet but you move it over to
some open source statistical programming
or machine learning environment or they
use some traditional statistical or
machine learning environment and they
when they build a model and then they
build a very good model and they use a
XG boost I'm going to use random forests
and they'll publish papers about how
good that that model is but once they
have that Eureka moment then they need
to somehow apply that model to the rest
of the data and where's the data
well they oftentimes took a sample or an
extract out of this larger data
repository or data Lake and for them to
apply that model they have to leave the
logic of the model back into oftentimes
a relational database in for enterprise
Oracle focuses largely on sort of larger
organizations and enterprises and so
oftentimes what people will do is
they'll recode the logic of that model
back into sequel and the TD WI firm
Halpert the data warehousing Institute
says that this is the industry average
is nine months nine months to
operationalize a predictive model I know
guys that you know you know reputable
banks that data scientists that say oh
I'm on the hook I'm in trouble charlie
I'm on the hook I got to do two maybe
even three predictive models this year
and or where this technology is going
and certainly where we're or was lent
away is to move the algorithms to the
data data is big and it keeps on getting
bigger and bigger
algorithms are small so why don't we
teach that data management platform how
to do math so if you do that it really
changes everything and I have a friend
he was the VP of data Sciences at a
nearby bank here in the Boston area and
he reached out to me before I knew him
and he said Charlie I use your product
it's the best thing out there for check
fraud and I asked him oh are is that
because you're using our new anomaly
detection algorithm
that's that's good at detecting a very
very rare events like less than 1% as we
train on normal and and then we flag
things that are sort of dissimilar to
normal kind of like Big Bird and it is
pointless no no I have lots of examples
of check fraud so I use a standard
classification I think he was even using
them and he was using logistic
regression sort of the classic technique
but for him the advantage was and this
is where I kind of part ways with some
data scientists who think it's all about
the algorithms to me it's all about the
data and the derived data and what we
sometimes call the engineered features
so for for this particular data
scientist we eventually hired him his
notion was I am going to look at a
moving window of time in the database
there's something called sequel
windowing functions maybe other vendors
have the same kind of concept but it's
taking a moving window of time and like
to say the past six months and it's
gonna say what's the average number of
checks that you've written what's the
average amount of those checks what's
the min what's the max and so you know
you have 5 or 10 variables there's this
moving average of the window of time and
you also generate another variable that
is the most recent 24 hours for those
same let's say 6 variables and they need
to arrive another derived or engineered
feature that is the difference between
the longer term behavior and the more
recent behavior because that's what
check processors do they they set up an
established credit they they they have a
normal account and then they go berserk
and start writing all sorts of checks
people the banks who catch them and
those 18 variables in this sort a simple
example are really nothing you haven't
even put it through a neural network or
logistic regression it's those 18
variables that are cleverly derived
which is where all the you know domain
expertise lies and being able to then
immediately operationalize that because
it's just a it's just a pipelined sequel
query apol or to do all that that's how
you sort of really operationalize a you
know machine learning I think and one
thing that you mentioned is that is a
lot of it is not about the algorithms
it's about the data and the difference
in this other architecture that you talk
about and that you worked on at Oracle
is that the algorithms are
moving to where the data is yeah they
become part of the data management
platform when you install the data
management platform they come sort of
you know a library of machine learning
algorithms already embedded as part of
that data management platform or on the
cloud everything's in the cloud these
days of course what are the types of
algorithms that can be moved to where
the data is whoa
all of our albums are moved so I don't
want to do like a feature list of
Oracle's technologies but but you know
we have about 30 algorithms in the
inside the database for about 30 that
went on a Hadoop and spark environment
and so there's you know decision trees
k-means clustering logistic regression
generalized linear models near now
seeing the kernel support vector
machines one class support vector
machines market basket analysis we do
text mining all those kind of things
I guess I'll briefly explain how we
started on this journey I don't want to
give away any kind of secrets but we did
this you know 15 or more years ago so I
don't think it's so much of a secret
today or or at least again to get an
idea like you mentioned decision trees
can be moved to the database logistic
regression just a brief example of
decision tree can be moved to the data
and with that you can build an
application that does X Y X let me
explain how how say say say a naive
Bayes or an a priori market basket
analysis algorithm work they're they're
both the a priori is the market basket
the old beer in diapers story although
you know by the way that was not really
you know the story the story there was
way over told and became urban myth over
the years but hmm for those that are not
familiar weather can you explain that
diapers and beer story sure if they
haven't already heard it many times
before the computer in diapers story was
actually came out of its total different
ways it's either told as Walmart or
Moscow drums and that they noticed some
sort of correlation they found a pattern
of we're on I think was on Friday nights
they would find a high correlation of
beer being put in the basket is sold
diapers and so the story then that even
were enhanced and so then this osco or
walmart company then decided to move the
beer and the diapers gear to each other
right next to each other so the
whoever's buying diapers also buys beer
who's ever buying beer also buys the
diapers heads on home for the weekend
and sales went way up because of that
you google that a little bit there's
some good sources on sort of
demystifying or a full story they did
find a correlation but that was about it
but it but but anyway that the the
associations rule that was used there
basically just counts the number of
items let's say ketchup and hamburgers
and hot dogs and buns or spaghetti and
bottles of wine and so on and it counts
for each item that you that you have
what we do is we do frequent itemsets we
just count pairs of things and then we
take the frequent itemsets and do a
little bit more conditional probability
math on it and next thing you know we
have a an association rule if I see
ketchup and relish and hamburgers and
hotdogs all in a basket together then
there's a probably amount of eighty or
ninety percent probability that I would
also see hot dog buns and hamburger buns
and that may represent three percent of
all my sales going on to the door at the
poetry store but if I can bundle those
things together maybe I can sell more
Dunkin Brands has been a public
reference of ours that I can mention
that that have publicly talked about
their use of market basket analysis to
try and sell you know more than just
coffee those with doughnuts go to
doughnuts go with coffee but I think
publicly they've talked about trying to
elongate their day and sell sandwiches
p.m. to Black's I think they called them
later on in the day and so they wanted
to know what would go well with that a
lot of other companies that I've worked
with talked about making high profits
off of selling drinks sugary water you
know those huge profits on that so what
things could I sell potato chips salty
soups things like that that would cause
more takeout orders to include those
drinks but all that really is is just
using the database
things and so it's the easiest algorithm
to implement natively inside the
database naive Bayes is very similar it
just does conditional probabilities
let's say I am selling motorcycles and I
count how many times people buy the
motorcycles that they're 80 years older
80 years or older or 60 to 80 over 40 to
60 or 2130 and I just in the data I
count it and I the beginnings and the
conditional probability model and what
does it mean to have a native machine
learning algorithm implementation in the
database well we have them just to be
clear Oracle has them both in the
database which is where we've been do it
sort of for the longest but probably our
best most mature versions and all that
there we also have them outside the
database in the in in in the data Lakes
I'm going to do it in the smart world
and you can imagine you know being able
to export the models to other places and
put them into real time deployments
applications but but the the algorithms
in the in the database just means that
it just opens all these doors for a pure
application developer said before these
Oracle code events we had a lot of
interest in like well I'm a DBA or I'm a
developer and I'm not necessarily a data
scientist but I'd like to build a
predictive application so the ATM could
recommend you know take a charlie take
out an extra hundred s cash if I can
learn the patterns in the database then
at the end we codify those patterns and
relationships those inputs outputs um
say Oh regression or a decision tree or
whatever there at the end of the day a
first-class object they're secure
they're scalable everything and when I
run them is all fully paralyzed because
I'm taking advantage of all the
machinery of what are you know
enterprise relational database would do
so in the latest release that we've just
come out with a PF I think the specs are
something like you know over 600 million
records and over nearly 400 variables or
attributes and you want to and and 500
degrees of parallelism you could build a
decision tree or regression model in 1 2
or 3 or 4 min
so that just sort of changes everything
now that's the model building if you
have a if you have a model that takes
you a long time to build I would argue
you know let's say it takes a half an
hour and just don't have enough patience
you don't always just schedule it right
it's like a long run inquiry or
something a rapport but the beauty of
that is by now having that predictive
model the already built you know maybe
it took you four minutes and you did it
you know last night at midnight whatever
and you did like a hundred models now
every time you go to let's say an
airline or you check in and you check in
with the one suitcase and the one
additional person that you were that
were part of your party and then instead
you show up with 12 other people and 25
extra suitcases well that may look like
you're the coach of a sports team and
maybe they want to upgrade you or put
you on another flight or do some sort of
thing so being able to do that sort of
real-time it's what it's all about and
if that model is is just a actual sequel
function how to feel sequel procedure
but it's a core function that can keep
up with OLTP kind of demands and you
mentioned you have a support a hybrid
approach where some algorithms are
native in the database while other ones
you can be using Hadoop and things like
that
are there some types of problems that
are better solved when it's native
versus when it's not I don't think of it
that way I think of it more as where's
your where's your data and what makes
the most sense so I know I know a lot of
people you know there's there's sort of
this pendulum swing all towards you know
machine learning the normal towards
Hadoop and spark and those are very very
important technologies and trends that
we're all seen but I do think that
sometimes people sort of skip right over
the obvious which is what's the data
that you're gonna use for that to solve
that problem but let's say I am ready to
buy I have another I told you I'd
reference a couple of books another book
that I'm reading lately that I just love
is this book called the naked future by
Patrick Tucker that says what happens in
the world that anticipates your every
move
in the outlines a lot of different sort
of examples and scenarios that as soon
as you hear amigo of course that's gonna
happen so let's say I'm about to put in
a quarter into my vending machine
it's another coil it's in dollar and a
quarter to buy an Ice Cream Sandwich but
somehow in the world of big data I know
the source of that Ice Cream Sandwich I
know where it came from and maybe it
came maybe was manufactured in in Los
Angeles and I'm in Boston well there
might be in the big data world there
might be a bunch of sensors on delivery
trucks Ruby knows I cream ice cream
sandwiches from Los Angeles to Boston
and along the way it's saying yes it's
28 degrees it's nice chilly 28 degrees
going through the desert in Arizona and
so on it's still 28 degrees we just hit
a spike it's up to 40 degrees I don't
really care that it ever that was 28
degrees that's not an important variable
to me as long as it's never trips
anything I do care if it ever goes up to
40 degrees and more importantly I care
maybe do their ever go up to 40 degrees
for more than a half an hour because if
it did and my ice-cream sandwich I
probably don't wanna buy that one I want
to go somewhere else and so that data
might be in a data Lake I don't need us
to analog I don't have to bring the
algorithms to that data Lake to do the
analysis I may just want to do a derived
variable and what we call an engineered
feature to say did it come on truck 27
because truck 27 had 14 incidents of it
going above 40 degrees for more than a
half an hour and the driver of truck 27
and this data might be stored in the
database is Charlie burger and Charlie
burger has had so many accidents before
and the tires on the truck that Charlie
burgers driving or all bald and on and
on and on right I might not have
certification and I might go over a lot
of bumpy roads for my GPS tracking so
you really have to kind of think about
what problem I trying to solve in this
case it's should I buy that ice-cream
sandwich in the vending machine
and what's the data that that's that
supports that decision
in Show 286 intro to machine learning a
bit discussion that we had was around
data cleaning and the importance of this
in machine learning because a big part
of machine learning involves grabbing
features from different tables shaping
the data cleaning the data filling in
empty values if you want so I'm
wondering how does this work out with
when when the algorithm is implemented
natively in the database does the
database change and get cleaned also or
is it a copy well it's changed a good
place it the source data is always the
source data right let's say I have let's
say I have a customer data about the
address name that kind stuff I have
customer demographics about their
education their profession their their
income things like that and then I have
transactional sales transactions things
they purchase and now I have like a 306
maybe I've customer service comments as
well so I have some unstructured data as
well and I join all those two guys
together well I'm gonna join them in the
database just the way I would join them
in any other environment that one of the
advantages that of bringing the
algorithms to the data that I always
think is a really differentiator or
taking that approach is the data does
not have to be flattened out into a
well-behaved two-dimensional table right
when it comes down to like what what
drugs what transactions do you have what
purchases that is a that is just a
vector right it's a it's a vector and I
can tabulate the total number of
purchases of the year or mustard or
ketchup or wine or whatever and I can I
can bring those in as aggregates and in
fact I can even compare the aggregates
to others in the population as I said
before but let's say we bring all that
data together we've done a lot over the
years that I would argue some people
have maybe some people don't but if we
have missing values for example that
that struggle has been around for years
and what many people do and what we do
is we replace the missing value with
meat with a median or the or the mode
now that's default behavior we just do
that
it's called Auto data preparation
when you have something like age and
your target field is let's say
motorcycle yes or no
we tessellate or the space or carve up
the distribution of age intelligently we
have we have three different ways of
doing that
we can bin that the the age let's say
goes from negative five to 127 let's say
goes for 227 because I have bad data in
there so what we're gonna do is we're
gonna test like that either into ten
equal width bins starting out with
negative five all the way up to 227 or
I'm going to do equal count so I noticed
there's a lot more people in the twenty
to thirty thirty to forty there's very
few people and the two hundred and
twenty seven so I'm gonna collapse that
back down and I'll have equal with bins
or the most intelligent thing that we do
I think I call that I call a genius
meeting that the developers that wrote
it don't like that but but it really
cuts the space with respect to the
target field so wherever you have the
think of a growing a decision tree and
finding the cut points along just that
one variable with respect to the target
field and then once we find those cut
points well you can count and as we said
before if I'm simply counting then we
know what bins I mean I'm in bidding one
two three four five and I have five
hundred and twelve degrees of
parallelism wow I can do that
lightning-fast so all of the all of the
data preparation is what we would call
automatic data preparation in fact not
to go on our rant here but poor the
example in you know unstructured data
data management platforms over the years
have gotten very good very mature so in
the in the Oracle environment there's
something called Oracle text that simply
just token eise's the data so I have a
bunch of emails or paragraphs or
powerpoints or whatever it's gonna give
me a bag of words word count use this
the energy statistical kind of technique
and it's gonna do that in any language
I think in sports like sixteen I think
it's 32 languages actually it could be a
thesaurus or that and I gonna have a
single or multiple language and what's
gonna do when it gets to say Charlie
burger and my customer support comments
it's gonna say Charlie burger called up
his cable box was coming out with a
digital picture
pixelation way too many times and the
word pixelation might appear
17 times in my record over the last
three weeks well 17 times of the word
pixelation and angry and frustrated are
going to be compared to the larger
population using TF idea of the term
frequency inverse document frequency and
now we're going to have Charlie burger
my age my income what Kate what the
eight cable box generation is that I
have and all these unstructured comments
that have now been essentially structure
eyes din to a vector of coefficients or
how often I use those words versus
everyone else and and I can do all that
just as fast as lightning inside the
data management platform because as I
probably have said a couple of times we
moved to be algorithms to the data
management platform rather than the
other way around us because we inherit
all these other capabilities so so so
when you talk about predictive
applications which is the purpose of the
talk I I believe and you say well now I
can more easily do that but but also
I've got issues of like security
encryption maybe some of those emails or
comments that I have or my or my resume
or my health and medical records and I
don't want to export all of that out to
some separate open source or a
proprietary separate analytical server
that has maybe a lot less security
capabilities than you know a very
powerful industry leaders who have data
management platform hands so all the
algorithms all the math everything are
all sort of contained within that same
that same platform yeah and what working
on the database gets used like you
mentioned this automatic data cleaning
filling in missing values and things
like that
but when I was first starting to get
into machine learning and if you look at
most of the online courses and resources
like coggle where you can find a lot of
datasets they're all in CSV or txt files
why do you think that is well because
you're just you know you're just
starting out I mean though some of those
datasets are very famous simplest well
the txt it's the lowest common
denominator right so like the Allstate
Insurance data said in order
for me to use that at say any major
database player or open-source our
Python Microsoft IBM Terminator whoever
it's easy for me to take a ten thousand
record sample and send it around and
share it there's also some datasets that
over the years have just been very very
good there's a cars data set that then
every every status did statistical
company uses I go back so far that I
know the the person who want to generate
an at all original data center mr. Ramos
but but but some of those data sets are
just damn good data sets right they're
really good for showing correlations
between this and that the iris data said
everyone uses is just a CSV file and
then when you get into like the Enron
text mining data set and you know maybe
that's a more complicated JSON
representation some platforms we can we
can ingest JSON data others to you but
unfortunately that's that's why I say
there's there's just in my opinion a
little bit too much emphasis on I mean
there's a lot of people that need to
learn machine learning and I want
everyone to or didn't feel good with it
just the same way that people can all
use Excel these days right it's just you
know do you know how to use Excel well
of course you do right so do you know
how to use machine learning techniques
you know we of course you should write
but to learn you need small data sets
but to do realized a real one Enterprise
production applications of it you need
to take a look a lot more computer
science developers DBAs all that has to
come into play a lot more than so an
enterprise wouldn't really be converting
their database to CSV or txt for doing a
predictive application okay they're
doing that that that just seemed silly
yeah that you should not it I'll tell
you my favorite developer I guess I
can't mention him by name but he's he's
a DBA at a company that was doing real
time on something I don't want to
mention the name exactly but it's a
financial services they approved their
their public if you google my websites
up they'll see it financial services
they do predictions about whether or not
this money transaction of say $10,000
should be valid or not and and they used
to take the data out bring it over to
I'll call it a traditional statistical
package and they would build models and
it would take them three months to build
the models but more importantly to
the models and put him into production
because model as we said before it was
out there and and and they had to sort
of operationalize that and implemented
his sequel queries and logic if this if
this if that you know if they're
impeding twenty seven for age and this
in this now the DBA would be the person
that would assemble all that data do all
the transformations do all the joining
this table or this table of this table
together and finally put together all
the data and then send it over to the to
two people that I know that were PhD
data scientists and they would use you
know other traditional packages or they
convert it over to use our stuff and and
and they build it until very very good
models cuz they're brilliant people but
the DBA finally said wait a minute
you're taking all my hard work putting
all this data together and all you do
with the very end is press go on a
machine learning algorithm because
essentially that's what machine learning
is all about you're just using the
neural network or decision tree or any
kind of classification technique yes I
can do that myself so this DBA and
everyone was pretty pretty happy with it
was building models that were about
ninety-five percent the same accuracy as
the other PhD data scientists but
building them you know as an application
developer in DBA in in on the same
amount of time or less so that to me
that's what it's all about it's it's
transforming and extending your you're
sort of I'll say previously not the
smartest database in the world if you
just storing your data there it's a sort
of a file cabinet
now that database has become you know
more of a thinking machine type of thing
well you should have your app all your
applications should have not only
historical points of view but you should
have sort of affliction on every
variable you have you know what's my
income actual what's my predicted income
what's my checking account balance
what's my predicted checking account
balance and on and on and on there
should be a collection throat
essentially every variable you have if
you manage to store it there's actual
misprediction let's talk a little more
about native our algorithms in the
Oracle database when I was researching
for this I saw that you mentioned that
it's done by mapping our to sequel so
I'm wondering what does the our
programming language provide you with
it's a clarifier correct a little bit
will you what you said
we map our to sequel but our is a
language unto itself that that maps
turns out base our Maps a hundred
percent to base sequel right I can take
aggregates I can take select I can say
things of that sort and there are
equivalent basic sequel functions so all
the small verbs of our map one two one
two small verbs and sequels so we do
that we call the artists equal
transparency layer but but remember I
said we've we've already built in the
proprietary algorithms that we're up to
about thirty you know
generalized linear models support vector
machines mineral networks random forests
PCA sdd all these kind of things those
are all grown from the inside out of the
database in the way I described earlier
in the in the interview we they're
they're their proprietary aim database
highly paralyzed scalable
implementations of workhorse algorithms
their traditional and cutting edge and
so now along comes our and a lot of
people that know are well you can use
your base our language to to select the
data to query it maybe visualize it but
when you do something like say a box
plot box plot calculates the meeting in
the first second third and fourth
moments of the data if I have a billion
records I don't want to pull all that
data out over a single thread and open
source R to do that so what we do is we
in we see what you're trying to do and
we push it down so the calculations for
the min/max deviation on that are in
database sequel implementations of that
so if you have a billion records and 500
degrees of parallelism on your
enterprise database environment or it
cuz you're a bank or a telco or a
hospital or something that bar will
it'll be unbeknownst to do to me it's a
little bit like Google Translate right I
I typed something in one language and it
immediately translates it to the other
for high performance execution in the
database you know if you come in with
your script that you've already written
and includes our part a popular our
package for doing decision trees I'm
going to stop you at the border and kind
of say wait a minute don't come in here
with your are part you can if you want
to but I'm not going to add any value to
what you're doing your is going to take
the data maybe do some aggregations
maybe some data prep whatever you want
to do in the database
when it comes to using our part you're
going to do something called embedded
are where we do a call out through inter
process communication we're going to
take that data set we're going to do a
call out to your arm our part package
you're going to build the model and a
single threaded memory constrained now
maybe have a lot of memory and it's a
big box but you're still using open
source so hard to do that and I'm gonna
say you can do that if you want to but
you're paying a cost did you know that
we have an in database implementation of
decision trees all the Oracle data
mining the decision tree that can they
can that can actually handle structured
data unstructured data transactionally
and all these kind of things so so
before you want to port exactly your
honor script I'd say stop see if there's
an equivalent high-performance paralyzed
in database implementation of those
algorithms and use that instan you'll be
a lot happier and if there is still
something you want to do in our and you
can do whatever you want but let's say
there's a XG boost or something as the
example I use that's an arm package and
we don't have that yet and you find it
really important for some reason you can
do that what to call outside prescribe
described before but I would say you're
using are in that situation a little bit
more sort of analytical duct tape yeah
you mentioned base are is that a
different flavor of our or what is
basically it's just base it's just our
without all the packages right okay you
you get ggplot you get you know all the
different packages that you are part
whatever QC package and all the
different packages you load twice nine
or ten thousand packages in the our
community and I can download our and
they'll come in with essentially no
packages then I go to crayon and I
download whatever packages I find are
important to me and and and people will
download like deep wire well in our
latest release we added support for deep
layer so you can use the deep layer
commands and syntax you will when you
when you load up our Oracle advanced
analytics or in the cloud it's already a
little installed for you and in the
on-premises installs by default but but
when you when you when you use our
product and then you want to use open
source are you have to get an open
source are but then you you do sort of a
post or additional installation it's
already done for you in you know in an
Oracle managed cloud or so but we do we
add about a dozen or re I mean it
doesn't arm packages all Rhys tats or we
Mining ilaria graphic so are we this in
that in addition likes AOR we are
connect so the are connect that's in the
open source community Oracle are
connection that's maintained and open
source by Oracle but then we have
additional packages that it mapped to
our previously written proprietary you
know high-performance fully paralyzed
scalable albums you know you're gonna be
doing yourself a disservice if you don't
you know coming to look at the databases
as a possible platform to do your
analytics but you want to keep going and
use your our language and push down
further or use the drag-and-drop GUI the
Oracle data miner or you see which
generates sequel code and you can
integrate our code as well I won't go
into a whole product pitch here but but
if you do go take a look at it take a
look at the whole spectrum of what we
offer not not just the support for our
visitors that's that's that's probably
the best I've seen out there but there's
a lot more to it yeah the big data big
data we do the same thing we use an our
API and we have our proprietary
algorithms there as well and we wrap ml
lib and things like that mm-hmm
and two approaches of machine learning
are supervised and unsupervised
which of these two can be implemented
natively everything if I'm miss
communicating everything that we've done
is I seen rised unsupervised
they're all implemented so for
supervised it involves labeling the data
I have I don't know like the email
example we can let flag it as spam
meaning we write that column are we
altering the real data the real tables
with this supervised labels no it's
think of it as if it helps think of it
as like any other package SAS SPSS or
Python whatever you have you have the
data and then you in our case you don't
move the data to another analytical
platform so if it's label data or
unlabeled data whatever you know let's
say one of the variables is is this spam
is this email spam or is this patient
likely to have a none play let's say
let's say we go to let's switch to make
it more interesting let's go to a
hospital or a health care kind of
environment
patience they've all come in for
surgical procedures and I need to know
which ones I should be tracking because
they might have an unplanned surgical
readmission and that cost me a lot
if the Atlanta do rework if you will and
people die and it's just not good so you
have a bunch of people in the past that
have had to return to the to the to the
low are to have some more surgery so in
that case it's gonna be labeled you know
did they do a surgical you know might be
even flight like what was the data there
there it might be two dates date of
original on the date of Apollo up for
example we have Sean's I'm thinking
another peach we have something called
sequel patterns that detects like
dropped calls on you know I call you you
call me back I call you back
well if I noticed this dis and this I
could flag then as a dropped call so
let's say we use some sort of logic to
have a derived variable that says yes
this in fact was a person when unplanned
surgically readmission or this piece of
email is spam so that's just another
field if it's in the database right it's
it's a label but it's just on their
attribute in the database so if I want
to so if I want to do supervised or
unsupervised or whatever it's just like
any other there's no difference that I'm
maybe I'm misunderstanding the question
well I was just wondering like if if we
are using the real database tables
because in the other approach it
involves taking a copy of the data
running the algorithms but the real data
is not touched what I would meant was if
we're working with the real tables and
the real data and some of machine
learning involves adding additional data
like these labels of something in spam
or not what I meant was if the real data
was being modified or if there's a some
temporary tables that we work with well
you would do it you you would do it
however it made sense in you and let me
give you another example let's say I
have I'm trying to sell clothing and I
want to find people who buy a lot of
shoes and so I have shoe transactions
and I have customer let's say at Macy's
or or or
you know I don't know all the different
shoe stores but I mean no clothing
stores but Filene's basis when he's
going places and what word and Taylor
and I have I have purchases of people
and have their information and their
credit cards their transactions but I
also have all their transactions I could
do a tabulation of in the category of
shoes to have you late for the last year
but the total valuation was that's just
a sequel aggregate rent just a sequel
query and then I could do have a derived
variable that says and if this is more
than $500 create a new variable called
big spender big shoe spender right and
so that would be a new derived variable
that would go that would be either added
to the table you know of customer table
or maybe it would be another table that
said you know my data mining labels
however you choose to do that your DBA
is gonna maybe I'm gonna pinion on that
but then when I go to build my when I go
to build my model I would just take the
customers table and join it to the tag
data and I usually don't see it done
that way usually just see it as another
table joint you know added to the
customer table like high value standard
yet you know shoot a big shoe spender
yes
or maybe the dollar amount of them or
however I want to do that it's just pure
sequel at that point and then I build my
models now all I have to do now that I
have my predictions
I don't off the read I don't have to
repeat all that data and we just
actually build the join by the way could
be persisted as a table or more likely
just done as a view right it's just it's
just a it's just a few and I can
materialize that view or not there's all
sorts of standard things DBA guys would
do to your production eyes or
operationalize it that's why I was
saying in this Oracle code kind of event
we're sort of going to the next wave of
getting developers to go beyond just
official and narrow and predictive but
but they they would maybe a view and
then build the model they can probably
want to persist the model we do have
things called predictive queries that
build the models on the fly apply the
models on the fly throw the models away
and just return the results so you're
probably gonna say I'd like to tech to
interrogate that in Lobby you turn me on
for my credit or whatever you did what
logic did use when was that model
created so you probably want to store
and save the models but they're just
sort of first-class objects in the
database
and then when I make my predictions I
would say you know select customers
where the probability of them being a
big shoe spender is greater than 65
percent so now I have a model I have all
the data I just pushed that data through
the model as a sequel apply function and
in you know nanoseconds it scores maybe
millions of records and then I would
probably just want to you persist that
and it's just a sequel query at that
point it's a results table I probably
want to save that because I want to
probably graph that in some pie chart or
bar chart or someone that I put it on I
send the results out to my ATM or my
salespeople but I don't have to persist
you copy all the rest of the data I just
I just have the prediction like like yes
or maybe a dollar amount like $7,000 of
shoes for Charlie and and and if it's a
classification of the probability of
that we also do something called
prediction details which were regardless
of the album would give you like the top
in reasons why like you know because you
know we purchased a lot of shoes in the
past Ori he likes high-end shoes the
only buy is one pair but they're ten
thousand dollars a pair each year
whatever it is and though that would
only bring you one you know would bring
you what the prediction the probability
and maybe the rules table and so you
really only have any original data
maybe you create another attribute which
is the labels you build the model you
save the model for reuse or whatever and
then you had those three additional
attributes that's all it really is it's
very it's very light incremental load on
your on your when your enterprise system
and it actually makes a lot of sense and
it's very intuitive to the regular
workflow for using sequel I I've used it
since since I was in school and those
are the things that I would do I would
write a query like what you just
mentioned but it will be mostly like I
would have a table of people and a table
of hobbies and just a query that map's
the person with hobbies but now with
machine learning I can even add more
powerful insights like using the
probability that they would like to
watch a movie as a as a new hobby and
things like that which come from those
native implementations of algorithm
if I understand correctly yeah that's
that's exactly yeah it's kind of
exciting for you too for you to make
that comment because my experience has
been that you know I don't like the term
data scientist everyone is calling
themselves a data scientist today today
we eat to be a scientist you're supposed
to have a Tarbell degree with a PhD and
a lot of people call them substantive
data scientists they don't really you
know have that just uh you know control
over who calls themselves made a
scientist or not but but also that
there's this sort of culture that the
first thing I do is you know go get the
data for more of the data sources from
the data lake or the database or
wherever and then take it over to my
analytical sandbox and do my analytical
magic on it and and and it stops there I
mean the example I often write about man
with enough caffeine on board remember
it was the Netflix example right Netflix
offered a million dollars to the data
scientist team that could come up with a
better prediction so nobody they had to
do one percent better nobody came in one
percent better I think they came in 0.85
percent better if I remember it
correctly and they gave him the million
dollars regardless and so that made the
press everyone talked about that but
what no one remembers and this is one of
my operational customers uh included a
story in one of their presentations they
said what no one remembers is that
predictive model that better model was
never operationalized was never put into
use why it was just too much this outer
loop overhead complexity just they
didn't Netflix didn't think it was worth
worth that now if you go back to my DBA
story at the financial credit risk
transaction you know use case that DBA
is saying hey I do all my data my data
wrangling my data assembly my reports
whatever machine learning the good thing
about machine learning it's all
automated so I find that's a lot easier
and a lot more exciting about where this
technology is going to have developers
and DBAs we work with the data you know
what we're alone for them to
incrementally learn you know they're all
science and math majors for them that
you know remember that logistic
regression of course you took you know
ten or five years ago or 20 years ago
that same thing exists as another sequel
function in the database you too can do
that today and I find a lot more success
with customers who our database computer
science literate people who incremental
add the date of science and data
scientists who try to incrementally add
the whole complexities of an enterprise
data management platform they just can't
get from there to here as easily as the
developers can do or to me the big
insight was remember that logistic
regression or the math you learned in
high school
well that is machine learning yes
exactly it's had many names over the
years yeah exactly well Charlie thank
you for taking the time to come on the
show it's been great talking to you
about predictive applications and
machine learning thank you very much
thank you for having me thanks for
listening to se radio an educational
program brought to you by Triple E
software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at SC radio net to provide
feedback you can comment on each episode
on the website or reach us on LinkedIn
Facebook Twitter or through our slack
channel at SC radio.com you can also
email us at team @ SC - radio net this
and all other episodes of se radio is
licensed under Creative Commons license
2.5 thanks for listening